Katherine V. Leahy Papers VHP2005/9
CCSU Veterans History Project
Katherine V. Leahy Papers
Bulk, 1943-1945
1943-1945, 2005
VHP2005/9
CCSU Veterans History Project
47.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
The Collection details Katherine V. Tierney Leahy’s experiences during her enlistment in World War II where she served in Neurosurgery at Guam’s Fleet Hospital. Collection contains oral history interview, news articles and photographs. The papers, which date from 1943 thru 1946 and 2005, describe nursing practices during World War II, and highlight the recreational activities of service men and women on Guam.
Leahy, Katherine V., (Tierney), 1912 -
Biographical/Historical note
Katherine Leahy enlisted in the U.S. Navy, as a nurse in 1934. She lived in Bridgeport, CT at the time. Before joining the Navy she was a registered nurse working in a public hospital. She graduated with Bachelor of Nursing from Yale School of Nursing in 1934. She joined the Navy Marines because she had a younger brother in the Marine Corps and thought she might be able to take care of him. When she enlisted she received the rank of Ensign, and then reported to Norfolk (VA) for indoctrination. She then went to work in the naval hospital in Norfolk where she was assigned to the hospital ward. Her next assignment was the Naval hospital in Long Island (NY) where she taught female corpsmen, which she enjoyed, although she would have rather taken care of wounded soldiers. She then received orders to travel overseas to Guam. However, before she was transferred overseas she was stationed briefly in San Diego (CA) where she worked in a hospital for soldiers returning from the Pacific. In the end of 1944, she was sent to Guam. In Guam, her ship landed at Agana (Hagåtña), the capital of Guam. She was assigned to Navy Fleet hospital 111. The hospital had already been built but hadn't yet been set up with the equipment and supplies required to be fully operational. She worked on getting the hospital ready for operation. After the hospital was fully supplied, she worked in neurosurgical unit. Many of the patients Leahy worked on were casualties from the Iwo Jima campaign, and prisoners that were released at the end of the war. While working in Guam she was promoted to Lieutenant, Junior Grade (J.G.). She was also able to meet with her brother there when he was on his way to China. Her working conditions were good, and the hospital was well equipped. During the war she kept in touch with her family by mail. She left Guam in August 1945 and was then discharged from the navy. After the war, she kept in touch with some of her colleagues and joined the VFW. She worked at the Bullard company as an industrial nurse and then later worked with a private doctor.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Technical metadata of digital objects are extracted and encoded in PREMIS preservation metadata format
Preservation Metadata
Arrangement note
Series I: Presonal Papers
Series II: Publications
Series III: Multi-Media
United States. Navy Nurse Corps.; United States. Navy. Fleet Hospital 111.; Guam; Interviews; Iwo Jima, Battle of, Japan, 1945; Manuscript; Medicine, Navy; Military nursing -- United States -- History; Norfolk (Va.); Photographs; San Diego (Calif.); United States. Navy; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2005/9.I
  - Interview Sysnopsis, October 8, 2005; VHP2005/9.I.1
  - Interview transcript, October 8, 2005; VHP2005/9.I.2
- Series II: Publications, VHP2005/9.II
  - Article titled, “He’ll Drop His Books To Pick Up Rifle” highlights Thomas Tierney’s (Katherine’s brother) enlistment in the Marine Corps, Circa 1940s; VHP2005/9.II.1
  - Article titled, “He’ll Drop His Books To Pick Up Rifle” highlights Thomas Tierney’s (Katherine’s brother) enlistment in the Marine Corps, Circa 1940s; VHP2005/9.II.2
  - Article with photograph announcing the transfer of Ensign Katherine V. Tierney from St. Albans, L.I. Naval hospital to San Diego, CA Marine hospital, Circa 1940s; VHP2005/9.II.3
  - Article with photograph depicting military personnel from Bridgeport, CT stationed at the Army Air Force Training Command Radio School in Sioux Falls, SD. The four men and one woman are sending Christmas greetings to family members back home. Greetings were aired on U.S. radio station WNAB, Circa 1940s; VHP2005/9.II.4
  - Article published in the Reminder (Stafford Edition) describing Katherine’s enlistment and military experiences, November 16, 2004; VHP2005/9.II.5
  - Voices of Connecticut Veterans: Katherine Tierney Leahy and a Nurse’s Efforts in World War II, October 23, 2004; VHP2005/9.II.6; 9.0 pages
    General note
    Article detailing the life and military experiences of Katherine written by Eileen M. Hurst. The article titled, “Voices of Connecticut Veterans: Katherine Tierney Leahy and a Nurse’s Efforts in World War II,” describe Katherine’s motivations for enlisting in the Navy, her military training and appointments, and it highlights her extraordinary compassion and empathy for military personnel. This compassionate spirit was manifested after her military discharge with her involvement in the community, especially the VFW Women’s Auxiliary, and VFW Post 9990. This article was published by The Association for the Study of Connecticut History in the Fall 2005 edition of Connecticut History.
- Series III: Multi-Media, VHP2005/9.III
  - Subseries a: Still Images, VHP2005/9.III
    - Portrait of Katherine V.Tierney Leahy prior to her enlistment in the United States Navy., 1943; VHP2005/9.III.1
    - Katherine at her farewell party in Fairfield, CT, 1943; VHP2005/9.III.2
    - Katherine at her farewell party in Fairfield, CT, 1943; VHP2005/9.III.3
    - USMC Thomas Tierney, Katherine’s brother, 1943; VHP2005/9.III.4
    - Katherine standing outside her parents’ home in Fairfield, CT, 1943; VHP2005/9.III.5
    - Katherine outside her parents’ home in Fairfield, CT, 1943; VHP2005/9.III.6
    - Katherine (far right) and sisters (left to right: Betty Stiewing (nurse), Rita Anderson, and Sally Farrel)in Fairfield, CT, 1943; VHP2005/9.III.7
    - Katherine (left) with Sister Rita Anderson (right), Fairfield, CT., 1943; VHP2005/9.III.8
    - Katherine, St. Albans, Long Island, NY, 1943; VHP2005/9.III.9
    - Katherine in nursing uniform, 1944 - 1945; VHP2005/9.III.10
    - Katherine in dress uniform, 1944 - 1945; VHP2005/9.III.11
    - Katherine (left) and unknown Navy nurse, 1944; VHP2005/9.III.12
    - Katherine (far right) with a group of Navy nurses leaving St. Albans, NY for San Diego, 1944; VHP2005/9.III.13
    - Katherine (left) and unknown Navy nurse (right)., 1944; VHP2005/9.III.14
    - Katherine (right) and Ruth (left), St. Albans, NY, 1944; VHP2005/9.III.15
    - Katherine (far right) and Navy nurses, St. Albans, NY, 1944; VHP2005/9.III.16
    - Sarah Vaughn in Guam, 1944 - 1945; VHP2005/9.III.17
    - Graves of U.S. military personnel who died during the invasion of Guam, United States Cemetery, Guam, n.d.; VHP2005/9.III.18
    - States Cemetery with flag lowered to half staff, Guam, n.d.; VHP2005/9.III.19
    - Graves of U.S. military personnel who died during the invasion of Guam, United States Cemetery, Guam, n.d.; VHP2005/9.III.20
    - Katherine on beach, Tumon Bay, Guam, 1945; VHP2005/9.III.21
    - Leon Schieman, stationed at Air Force Base B-29, on the beach. Tumon Bay, Guam, 1945; VHP2005/9.III.22
    - Tumon Bay, Guam, 1945; VHP2005/9.III.23
    - Opening night at Officer’s Club VJ-17, 1945; VHP2005/9.III.24
    - Bernadette Terry (left) with Commander Turle of VJ-17, 1945; VHP2005/9.III.25
    - Navy Nurse Bernadette Terry (left foreground) and Army Nurse (right) dancing during opening night at Officer’s Club VJ-17., 1945; VHP2005/9.III.26
    - Three unknown officers enjoying opening night at the Officer’s Club VJ-17, 1945; VHP2005/9.III.27
    - performing at Officer’s Club VJ-17 opening night, 1945; VHP2005/9.III.28
    - Opening night at Officer’s Club VJ-17, 1945; VHP2005/9.III.29
    - Military personnel enjoying opening night at Officer’s Club VJ-17, 1945; VHP2005/9.III.30
    - Military personnel enjoying opening night at Officer’s Club VJ-17, 1945; VHP2005/9.III.31
    - Military personnel enjoying opening night at Officer’s Club VJ-17, 1945; VHP2005/9.III.32
    - Military personnel enjoying opening night at Officer’s Club VJ-17, 1945; VHP2005/9.III.33
    - Katherine (second from left) with unknown companions at Officer’s Club VJ-17 opening night, 1945; VHP2005/9.III.34
    - Katherine V. Tierney (second from left) with unknown companions at Officer’s Club VJ-17 opening night, 1945; VHP2005/9.III.35
    - Group of military personnel attending opening night at the Officer’s Club, Guam, 1945; VHP2005/9.III.36
    - Katherine returning to U.S. on board hospital ship, 1945; VHP2005/9.III.37
    - Katherine Leahy, Stafford Springs, CT, October 8, 2005; VHP2005/9.III.38
    - Katherine modeling the Navy nurse cape and hat she wore during World War II, Stafford Springs, October 8, 2005; VHP2005/9.III.39
  - Subseries b: Moving Images, VHP2005/9.IIIb
    - Oral history interview, October 8, 2005; VHP2005/9.IIIb.1; 1.0 dvd; Hurst, Eileen (Disk DVD VHP2005/9, Box VHP Interview #1)